Finding Aid for Health System Volunteer Services (University of Michigan) records, 1937-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Health System Volunteer Services (University of Michigan) records 1937-2006 1981-1995
University of Michigan. Health System. Volunteer Services.
2009058 Bimu 2
Volunteer service unit established at the University of Michigan Hospital in 1941. The Volunteer Services program expanded from patient registration and guide services to encompass a number of programs and outreach activities that extend beyond the hospital. The materials in the University of Michigan Health Systems Volunteer Services collection contain information on the service beginning with its formal establishment in 1941. Items include topical files, photographs, and audiovisual materials covering programming, volunteer recruitment, and especially volunteer recognition.
5.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 10150 ) was received from the unit in January 2009.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The records are open without restriction.
On January 3, 1941, Hospital Director Harley Haynes proposed the establishment of a volunteer service at the University Michigan Hospital. The proposal was well received and Kathryn Walsh, former clerical supervisor of out-patient clinics, was appointed as director. Walsh visited the volunteer departments in hospitals located in Detroit, Michigan and Cleveland, Ohio to gather information about establishing a similar program at the University Hospital.
Having gathered ideas for the structure of the program, its duties, and its uniforms, Miss Walsh visited area ladies and church organizations in Ann Arbor to recruit volunteers. March 31, 1941, marked the first official day of active Volunteer Services. These early volunteers served as receptionists in the Registration Department. They greeted patients, took registration cards, and served as hospital guides. By May 1941, nine active volunteers had given 85 hours of volunteer time. Volunteers were often young housewives or single young women who were not employed full-time. New volunteers were recruited through newspaper articles, letters of invitation, and informational teas.
By June 1941, participation more than doubled with 21 active volunteers giving a combined 100 hours a week. Volunteers were now serving in the surgery and medical clinics. The first University of Michigan students to participate joined in October 1941. In March 1942, soon after the United States entered World War II, the Volunteer Services registered with the Civilian Defense Volunteer Office. The hospital faced a staffing crisis as orderlies, ward helpers, and others left to join the armed services. Volunteers from the community and students from the university stepped forward. In April 1942, at the service's one-year anniversary, there were 74 active volunteers who had given a combined total of 4,033 hours.
The Volunteer Services branched into more of the hospital's departments. Volunteers worked in the patient's library, delivered food trays, read to patients, wrote letters, ran errands, answered phones, and served as guides to the hospital. With an eye toward expanding volunteer services, the department established a cart service in December 1943 to take candy, cigarettes, tobacco, and magazines around to the wards. This saved the nurses aides from having to run down to shop for patients.
In 1954, Volunteer Services began recognizing their volunteers with an annual recognition ceremony. The tradition has continued to present with volunteers being recognized for years of service. On November 2, 1959, Volunteer Services opened the Guild Gift Shop at the hospital. The gift shop was financed through fund raising and fund matching.
Over the years, Volunteer Services has grown from its original home in the "Old Main" Hospital to serve in the Taubman Medical Center, C.S. Mott Children's Hospital, the Women's Hospital and additional medical centers in Ann Arbor. Volunteers have served in many capacities at the hospital in programs like Adopt-a-Room, Thera-paws, and Parent-to-Parent Support, among others. The programs have extended beyond the hospital to include Meals on Wheels and other community outreach opportunities. Further information about the University of Michigan Health Systems Volunteer Services can be accessed at their web-page: http://www.med.umich.edu/volunteer/
The University of Michigan Health System Volunteer Services collection covers the years from 1937 to 2005. The majority of the material covers the years 1979-2000. The records include some history and establishment information, but a majority of the information deals with the annual volunteer recognition program. There is also a significant amount of photographs, including photographs of individuals volunteering as well as photographs from the annual volunteer recognition program. The collection has been organized into five series: Topical Files, Publications, Volunteer Recognition, Audio-Visual Materials, and Ephemera.
Subjects:
Hospitals--Michigan.; Student volunteers in medical care--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Health System. Volunteer Services.; University of Michigan. Health System.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; Volunteer workers in medical care--Michigan.
- Topical Files 1937-2003
  The Topical Files series (1937-2003) is arranged alphabetically. It includes administrative data such as annual reports, programming information, volunteer recruitment, and a scrapbook pertaining to the establishment of the program in 1941.
  - Administrative 1993-1999 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Community Outreach Programs 2003, undated (Box 1)
  - Handbooks for Volunteers 1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Parent-to-Parent Support Program 1996 (Box 1)
  - Recruitment for Volunteers undated (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook and Journal of Volunteer Services 1937-1943 (Box 1)
  - Thera-Paws Program 2001-2002 (Box 1)
- Publications 1974-1998
  The Publications series (1974-1998) is arranged alphabetically and then by year. It contains publications and newsletters produced by the volunteer service for its volunteers. Newsletter titles include Cheery Cheery Chit Chat, Smock Talk, Volunteer Services News, Caring for Generations and Volunteer Express. Also included are several folders of newspaper clippings of articles that mention the service. The newspapers include those produced by the hospital, those produced by the University of Michigan, and the local Ann Arbor newspaper.
  - Calendars 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1974-1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (various titles) 1975, 1979-1989 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (mainly Caring for Generations), 1990-1998 (scattered) (Box 1)
    [See also: Box 5 Oversize Material
  - Volunteer Express, 1986, undated (Box 1)
- Volunteer Recognition 1954-2005
  The Volunteer Recognition series (1954-2005) holds documents pertaining to the recognition of the unit's volunteers. Records include themed invitations, promotional materials, and honoree lists for the volunteer recognition banquets.
  - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - 1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1985 (Box 1)
  - 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989 (Box 2)
  - 1990 (Box 2)
  - 1991 (Box 2)
  - 1992 (Box 2)
  - 1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994 (Box 2)
  - 1994 50th Anniversary Book (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1997 (Box 2)
  - 1998 (Box 2)
  - 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - 2002-2005 (Box 2)
- Audio-Visual Materials 1940s-2005
  The Audio-Visual Materials series (1940s-2005) is arranged alphabetically by categories and subjects. Many of the earlier photographs appear to be copy prints. There are three sub-series: Mounted Photographs, Photographs, and Videocassettes. Photographs make up a majority of the series. Of these photographs, many are of volunteers in the hospital volunteering or of the Volunteer Services recognition programs. Also included is a slideshow for recruiting volunteers, several CD-ROMs containing digital photographs, and videocassette tapes with photograph shows presented at the annual volunteer recognition program.
  - Compact Disc (CD) Photographs, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 2)
  - Digital Video Disc (DVDs), 1 optical disks DVDs (Box 2)
  - Mounted Photographs
    - Assorted undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Costumes undated (Box 2)
    - Crafts and Arts undated (Box 2)
    - Gift Shop undated (Box 2)
    - Patient Library undated (Box 2)
    - Small Mounted undated (Box 3)
    - Large Mounted undated (Box 3)
      [See: Boxes 5-6 Oversize Material]
    - Volunteers and Children undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Volunteers and Senior Citizens undated (Box 3)
  - Negatives undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - Volunteers volunteering Undated (Box 3)
    - 1984, 1987, 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994, 1996 (Box 3)
    - 1997 (Box 3)
    - 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
    - 2000 (Box 3)
    - 2001 (Box 3)
    - 2002 (Box 3)
    - 2004 (Box 3)
    - 2005 (Box 3)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1983-1991 (Box 4)
  - Slides 1986-1987, 1990, 1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Slideshow Cassette Tape 1986 (Box 4)
  - Videocassettes
    - "A Gift for Yourself: Volunteering at the University of Michigan Medical Center," 1993 (Box 4)
    - "Volunteer Services 50th Anniversary," 1994 (Box 4)
    - Recognition 1995 (Box 4)
    - Recognition 1999 (Box 4)
    - Recognition 2003 (Box 4)
    - "Picture the Difference You Make," 2005 (Box 4)
- Ephemera
  The Ephemera series (1984, 1997, and undated) contains material relating to the Volunteer Services including: a 40-year anniversary button, a volunteer nametag, and a "thank you" coaster.
  - Ephemera 1997, 1984, undated (Box 4)
- Oversize Material
  (contents described above)
  - Oversize Material (Box 5)
  - Oversize Material (Box 6)